Hi everyone, in our roadmap video
series, we will start with the
module one or a phase
one, which is basically Python
foundations. So, in this session,
we will start with the
concept called object oriented
programming, which is also called as
OOPS. So, this is
not the basic Python guys.
It's a little bit of advanced
Python. If you are a complete
beginner and if you don't know
regarding anything Python,
I recommend watching these
videos. I have already made a
playlist called agentic AI full
course. I have added
all of these videos starting into
what are Python ,variables ,
functions ,
data structures ,
all of these things. And these
foundations are very important
before
we start with the new concept,
which is called OOPS. These videos,
I recorded two years
back. Even now, all these are really
good content. So, it is an English
format.
But moving forward, so if you are a
complete beginner, I recommend
watching those videos
If you look at the
first one, which is one point one,
which says
Core Python
In this, we need to learn all of
these points. And all of these
points are already covered
in these videos. So, I'm not going
to cover them again. Do you
remember? In our last
video, we have shown this resume JD
Tailor agent and we have built this
from scratch.
So I will just show you the code
base of this one. So, this is the
code base
of the same application.
And then I will just open this.
And if you look at the
code here, maybe if you are new to
the Python, you cannot understand
anything.
But don't worry, our end goal is
that by the end of the OOPS concept,
you will be able
to understand all of this code base.
If you look at this, there is
something called as
data class and class. What is this
class? What is LLM config?
What is a class method?
What are these and what are these?
If you don't know OOPS concepts,
you won't understand
all of this. If you look at the
other one, all of these uses OOPS
concepts completely
because at the production level,
if you want to write any code,
you need to use
classes. I
can achieve this without using OOPS
concepts.
That's why I have created one more
code base here. And if you look at
here, it's
also the same code base, but we are
not using any of the classes.
But if you write this code and send
a push request or a merge request to
a company,
no one will accept the code because
almost 99.9 % of the times you will
write the code
in the class format, not in the
normal functions format.
So that is why we are going to learn
this new concept which is called
object oriented programming.
What is this?
How to use?
Techniques Covered
Everything we will learn step
by step with some small basic
examples. Our end goal is that by
the end of this series,
I can cover all these concepts in
one video. So we are going to break
them into maybe
two or three videos. By the time
three or four videos are done,
you will be able
to understand what this code base
is. This code is written by an AI
agent. Now the next question
is, if the code is being written by
an AI agent, then why should we
learn all this?
It looks too complex, right?
So don't be afraid of code.
But before that,
let me show you one small story.
If you go to the news and if you see
this news,
an AI -powered coding tool wiped out
a software company's database,
then apologized for the
catastrophic failure on my part.
That is, the claude code in a
company, in the production level,
it has deleted the entire database,
guys. That is, it has almost destroyed
the company.
And after deleting, it just
apologized because it's a failure on
my part. So an AI agent,
it could be a cloud, a codex,
a gemini, a grok, if you don't know
what it is doing,
what it is writing, then you are in
no way an agentic AI engineer.
So the thing
is, you should be able to drive the
AI. AI should not be able to drive
you.
Then you will be able to sustain in
the market like this. Enough of all
of these things,
why do we need OOPS? We will start
with learning what is an OOPS and
allow every single detail.
So I am using VS code,
guys. Visual Studio code.
If you don't know how to set up
Visual Studio code, I will link a
video in the description below. You
can go and check
that out. So don't worry at all.
So next, folder creation,
which is called OOPS
concepts, inside that,
I'm using a Python file,
which is called OOPS part one.
So we will use
this one. And then we will learn all
the concepts regarding OOPS in this
notebook.
So let me close this explorer site
so that we have a lot of real estate
and let me
zoom in. So first, let's say,
we want to build an HR system in a
company called Infosys.
So what should HR do? They need to
save employee details.
Employee details could be
first name, it could be last name,
it could be salary, and maybe Gmail
So let's say,
I will create a first employee,
I will say employee one,
and I will put his first name
equal to Rahul. And then
I will create employee one,
last name equal to Sharma,
and then I will say employee one,
email equal to, we will use the same
formula,
which is basically first name plus
last name and @ company name,
basically. So I will
create a new employee, which is
Rahul dot Sharma at the red
Infosys dot com, and employee
one salary, we will take it as a
pay, which is basically 50,000,
let's say. So this is how
an HR can save an employee details.
It could be first name, last name,
and email, and pay.
So what if there is one more
employee? So what will you do then?
We will just keep it
as employee two, first name,
employee two, last name, employee
two, email, and employee
two, pay. So I will change the
details here like Priya,
and then maybe I will put it
as Patel, and then Priya dot Patel,
Priya dot Patel at the red Infosys
dot com, and
salary is 40,000, let's say.
So like this, I can save my employee
details, but what
if there are 200,000 employees?
So what will you do then?
So are you going to
sit and write these four lines of
code 200,000 times? You can't,
right? Even
if you do that, there is a lot of
chance that you are going to make a
mistake. So
what if at some point you messed up
this variable? Maybe the details
messed up. You
are going to change every single
thing, right? What if you need to
add some more
attributes, let's say,
employee one dot address or city?
City, I would say
Hyderabad. So now we want to add a
new attribute. So you have to go to
200,000
employees and add this line every
time, right? So it is not
sustainable. It is
not at all a production level.
So what will you do then?
So you can ask, why
can't I just use functions?
Functions you say, I can solve this
problem, right?
Yep, absolutely, you can use
functions. So what if I create a
function which is
called define, create an employee,
and it is going to take these
values, which
is basically first, last,
and pay. And then I will put it as
this one, and I
want to build my email.
Email is my summation of my first
employee
name and then the last name,
which has dot, and then after that,
so I will create f,
f string, and then I will say first
dot lower, and then dot,
and then dot here, and then last dot
lower at the rate in fosys.com.
And then
I can just return, I will return a
dictionary. I would say I will
create a
dictionary, which is basically
first, and then first,
and then last,
last, and
then email, which is my email
that we built here, and then which
is my pay.
I would say pay. So what are we
doing? We created a function like
this.
In this, it will take the first,
last, and pay. Then after that,
we are
creating the email based on my first
name and last name. After that,
we are
returning a dictionary,
which contains all the details of
the employee.
So employee details, I can just say
employee one equal to,
I can call this
one create employee, and then I can
pass these values, which is my
Rahul,
which is my first name,
and then I will provide my last
name, which is my
Sharma, and then I will provide my
pay, which is 50,000 rupees,
and then if
I print my email employee one,
I'm going to get all of these
details.
So let's execute this part and see
first name Rahul, last name Sharma,
email,
Rahul enforces, and then pay is 50
,000. So I can create my functions
and
I can manage as many as possible,
maybe 200,000 employees,
300,000
employees. Yeah, definitely.
But what if I want to increase my
salary to
my employees? So I can create one
more functions, maybe let's say
apply raise, and then it is going to
take what is my employee details,
and
then what is the percentage I am
going to increase the salary.
So I can put it here, and I can say
employee, and then I will just say
pay.
We are going to enhance or we are
going to edit the value of my pay,
which is basically
employee pay
into 1
plus percentage by
100.
So what are we doing here? We have
employee pay initially,
which is 50,000.
We are trying to access that
employee pay, and I take employee
pay
50,000 into how much percentage we
are increasing and how much
percentage
we are adding. And then if I just
say, after this, I will just call
this
function, which is apply raise,
and apply raise, I will provide my
employee
1 here instead of employee,
and I will put a percentage of 4
percent,
and if I just print employee 1,
it is going to give me the whole
thing
after the pay raise. If you look at
this one, initially we have
first name Rahul, last name Sharma,
and email RahulSharma at
the rightinfoces.com, and pay 50,000
is good. But once we applied
the raise of 4 percent,
the pay is 52,000. Now the thing is,
what if you want to change or you
want to add even better,
if you want to multiply more,
if you want to do more mathematics
operations, you can create multiple
functions. But the issue
is, these functions and the data are
disconnected.
Because you are calling all these
individually, there is no
one blueprint that says all these
should be connected.
So what is a class? A class is
basically a blueprint for
creating objects.
I need to save employee information
or all the things
I need to save in one place.
So for that, I can create a
employee details, you need to have a
blueprint,
and that blueprint is called a
class.
So to create a class, there is
something which is called
as class, and I will put it as
employee.
P -L -O -Y -E. So if you look at
this one,
and then I will put as a pass.
So what is this?
So class is basically a keyword in
Python,
and we will use it for creating
classes,
and employee is basically a class
name.
So class name, there are some rules.
You can use
something which is basically camel
case. So every
first important letter,
you will keep it in caps lock,
and second important letter,
you will keep it in caps lock.
Let's say a class is created,
which is Balaji Chippada.
So I can create Balaji,
and then C capital
Chippada. It is not like Balaji
underscore
Chippada functions names.
These are some rules
you can create some other things,
but it is always better to follow
the standard conventions.
How to create a class?
Using a keyword which is called
class, and then the class
name, and you follow this format,
and then
we are giving it as a pass for now,
because
code should be written inside,
but even if you don't write any
code,
Python will not give you an
execution error when you keep it
as pass. So that's why for creating
a default
class, we are keeping it as a pass
for now.
So we already have a class employee.
I will create an employee one,
and I will call this class,
which is basically
employee, and I need to provide this
instance.
And then if I want to create one
more employee, I can
just say employee two,
and I will just do employee,
and I will just do this.
Let's print both of these employee
ones.
Print employee one, and then also
print employee two,
and let's execute this.
And the output, it says
both employees are employee
object. So when you create an
employee one,
it's a variable. Using the class,
it is creating
an object of this class.
See, employee
object, and the location is at this
point, and employee two
is also creating an employee object,
and
it is at this location.
So they have different
memory addresses. They are unique
and separate
objects. And this is how you create
an instance of that
class using the class name.
So naturally, we are not having any
details
in the employee. So at the end of
we need to add the employee details.
So I can add the employee details
using dot. EMP one dot,
maybe let's say first,
and then I will keep it
as Rahul,
and EMP one dot last,
I will keep it as Sharma,
and then EMP one dot email,
I will keep it as Rahul dot
Sharma at the right
infosys dot com, and EMP one dot
pay,
which is basically
50,000 rupees.
And then let's print
EMP one dot email,
EMP one dot email.
So let's execute this,
and see,
Rahul dot Sharma at the right
infosys dot com.
If you look at this, VS code is
throwing an error.
It cannot assign to attribute first
for the class
because it is not a standard,
but if you look at the output,
it is not throwing any error
because it is not a standard,
but you can create
the details like this.
If I want to add employee two
details, I can just add like this
and I can access any of the employee
details,
employee two dot email.
If I want to access any of the
employee details,
I can execute this, and I can get
Rahul dot Sharma
and Priya dot Patel at the right
infosys dot com.
It is working fine, but it looks
terrible.
What is the use of the class?
You can create a class,
but if you are writing something
like this,
this is very terrible because what
if there are 200,000 employees
again, and it is going to throw the
same problems
it is going to repeatative
and it is not easy to maintain,
and there is no guarantee that you
will not make any mistakes,
and then it is always very
cumbersome.
It is not at all an ideal scenario.
So if you look at this one,
for every employee, what are we
saving?
We are saving the first name,
we are saving the last name,
and we are saving the email and the
pay.
So by default, we need all of these
things, right?
So is there any better way to save
all of these things?
Yes, that is where the main init
method will come into picture.
Within a class, you can write
methods.
So these methods are like basic
definitions,
like function definitions.
So I can just say define,
which is basically a keyword
on how you define functions in
Python.
I will say underscore underscore
init underscore underscore.
And within this, you provide
something
which is called as self by default.
What is this Self?
I will clarify what self means in
some time
because a lot of people have a lot
of doubts.
After this, we are going to take all
of these variables,
which is basically the first and the
last,
and then maybe let's say pay.
And the email, we will build it from
using first name
and last name.
And this init function of a
speciality is,
whenever you execute this class,
or whenever you create an instance
of this class,
this function is going to get
executed by default.
This init function.
So let me repeat.
Whenever you create an instance of a
class,
this function, which is basically
the init function,
is going to get executed by default.
Now this function is getting these
values,
which is basically first,
last, and pay.
And I am going to save all of those
things
inside these parameters.
To define these parameters,
you need to use self.
Self dot first equal to,
I will put it as first.
Sorry, I will put it as first.
What you can do here is,
here self is the important stuff.
Here self dot first is the variable
that we are assigning
and then we are giving the value as
first.
You can keep it as Balaji.
You can keep it as any kind of
variable name.
But as an industry standard,
it is always recommended to use the
same value
that you are providing here as the
variable name.
So it is easy to understand
what the industry is also doing.
After that, I will just do self dot
last.
I will get it as last.
And then I will just do self dot
pay.
I will get it as a pay.
So if I have to summarize how to
create a class,
this first one is called the
keyword,
which is called class keyword
that you have to use for defining a
class.
Then this is my class name.
And then inside this you have this
Dunder method,
which is the init method.
If function a more than that,
it will get executed by default.
Executed by default.
And it will take three parameters
right now.
One is the first name,
last name, and the salary.
And you are going to save those
three values
inside self dot first,
self dot last, and self dot pay.
So what did we do?
We created a class which is called
employee.
Inside this, we created the Dunder
method
and you created the instance of that
class
using a variable called employee1.
And we passed all of these details.
But the interesting stuff is,
when you create an instance like
this,
what Python does is,
this employee1 will be replaced
inside self animata.
So here, this will be employee1.
So when you create a new instance of
the same thing,
which may be, let's say,
employee2.jp,
that self will become the employee2.
And let's say employee,
and I will say priya,
and then I can do patel,
and I will get 40,000 salary and
then priya.
So when I execute this,
this self will be replaced with this
employee2.
So that is why self is mandatory.
So this will be acting as a
placeholder.
And whenever you are creating an
instance of that class,
this self will be replaced by this
internally
and you can access this as well.
Now if I want to print the details,
I can just do print employee1.last
and I can execute this.
And if I want to print employee1
.last,
and then if I want to print
employee2 first,
employee2.first,
and I can execute this,
and I get priya.
Now in our initial code,
we have different different lines of
code
for the same kind of purpose,
but when you create a class like
this,
you can reduce that point.
And the second question is,
what if I want to also create my
email?
I can create a variable here,
I will say email,
and I will build that email
using the first and last.
So here my first value is present
inside self.first.
Either I can use self.first
or maybe I can directly access
first.
So what do I do here?
By using f string,
I can put first.lower
.last
.lower
@ infosys.com.
Now what did we do?
We used our first name and last name
and created the email as well.
So if I want to access the email
of the first employee,
employee1.email,
I can directly access
because whenever you create
an instance of an object,
it is going to define all of these
things
by default.
And if I execute this,
see here,
sharma rahul.sharma at the rate in
infosys.com
So by default,
whenever I create an employee name,
I don't need to create my email.
This function will be creating
that email by default for me.
So this is much, much cleaner,
right?
And this is one line per employee.
If you look at this,
only one line per employee
and all the attributes like first
name,
last name, pay, email
are guaranteed to be set.
And now there is something
which is called as instance
variables, guys.
So what are instance variables?
What do we mean by instance?
Whenever you are calling a class,
that means you are creating
an instance of that class.
So employee1 is an instance of that
class
and employee2 is an instance
of that class.
So let's say I have this class
and I created two instance of that
class
which is basically employee1 and
employee2
and I can access employee1.first
and employee2.first
and I am going to get all of my
details.
So if I execute this,
see here,
rahul and priya.
Now the interesting stuff is
what if I want to change
the salary of the employee1?
So if I employee1.pay
which is basically our pay,
so we are going to change it to 8,50
,000
from the initial example
which is 8,00,000.
So if I do that
and if I print the pay,
it is going to update that
for that particular instance
only for employee1.
Employee2 value hasn't changed yet.
So if I go back here
and if I do the pencil stuff,
so what is happening here
you are creating an instance
of the employee1
and then you are creating
an instance of employee2
and then we are changing
the value of employee1 here.
So when you are changing
that particular employee1 value
which is the initial instance of the
class,
you are only going to affect
the employee1 instance.
Employee2 instance
is going to stay same
unless and until you make
the changes.
And this is also very important one.
So think of instance variables
like the information
on your Aadhaar card.
So eveyone has Aadhaar card
with the same class
but the name,
the detail,
the address,
all of them is going to be changed.
So that is why
it is very important to understand
when you change a particular values
in the particular local instances,
that particular instance
is going to get affected
but not the other ones.
Now what you have done is
now you have created
an instance employee1
and employee2.
What if you want to look
at all the details
of the instances.
So what you have done is
employee1 dot underscore
underscore dict
there is a method
it is an internal method
you don't need to worry
about that.
If you execute this
it is going to give you
all of the details
first name,
Rahul, last name,
Sharma pay 8 lakhs
and email is
Rahul dot Sharma
@infosys.com
That means
all the variables
So all of this
you will get
in a single dictionary
and that is what
this dictionary is.
Now the second topic
which is basically
the methods inside
a class.
Now you have created
two employees
what you want is
you want to print
the full name
print the full name
of the employee.
What you can do is
I can just do
print employee1 dot first
and then comma
and then I can put
employee1 dot last
and I can get
my full name
of my employee
which is Rahul Sharma
but how many times
do you create
what if there are
so many employees
so what you can do is
you can create
a custom method
method is basically
a definition
inside a class
maybe let's say
I want to create
a full name
I will create
a definition
of the class
and in this
by default
it is going to
take the parameter
which is basically self
then inside this
what I will do is
I will return
my full name
which is
here
I cannot directly
access first
because
I need to access
this as
the self dot first
because self
is very important
inside a class
and your employee1
is present in the self
right
so I can just do
self dot
first
and then space
I will just do
self dot last
if you don't want
how hard
it is
always remember this
whenever you are creating
any functions
or methods
inside a class
by default
the first parameter
is going to be
the self
and the
init and a method
you need to
create all the variables
using self dot and juby
and then whenever
you are accessing
those variables
inside the
particular class
always access
using the self method
self dot first
self dot last
directly access
that is how
I remember at least
and now
if I want to
get the
full name
I can just say
employee1 dot
I can call this
function
which is my full name
dot full name
and let's execute this
I mean
I need to
call it with the
parenthesis
and then
see
Rahul Sharma
we wanted to
print the full name
of an employee
so for that
we created a
method
this is called a
method inside a class
and
this method
is applicable
across all the
instance of the class
if I want to
print the employee2
full name
I can just do
employee2 dot
full name
and I can execute
this
I can get
Priya Patel
let's say
I want to
increase the
pay of an employee
so I can create
one more
function
let's say
increase def
increase pay
and I can say
self comma
I can take a value
which is called
percentage
and then
I need to
make the
modification
so I need to
modify the
pay dot value
whether
I can just say
self dot pay
equal to
which is myself dot
pay
into
maybe
I will keep it as
an integer
I want to make it
as a round
and then
I will
into
1 plus
percentage
by 100
and then
I just need to
close this one
I created
one more
method inside the
class
and if I need to
make the
change of a pay
to an employee
I can just call this
class
so let's say
I create this first
employee
and I will just
print my pay
initially
which is before my
change
and then once it is done
I will call this
function
employee one dot
increase pay
and then I will
provide
what is my percentage
maybe let's say
4 percent I want to
increase
and I will just do
the print of employee
one dot pay
after this
increase
and if I execute this
initially it is
8 lakhs
and then
which is basically
4 percent
increase
so like this
you can create
multiple methods
inside a class
and all of these
methods
will be able to
accessed
by the instance
that you created
here
what are we solving
we have a
particular class
employee
we are tying up
every single
thing
inside this
so this is what
the class
will solve
the functions
cannot do
so functions
you cannot have
this linkage
that classes and methods have
before we close
this call
there are two ways
to call
a method
actually
I can just do
employee one dot
I can say
increase pay
I can call like this
and I will provide
what is the value
or else
I can call it
with something
by the
class name itself
I can say
employee
dot
full name
and then
maybe
let's say
increase pay
and then
I will provide
what is my
employee one
maybe
let's say
employee one
and then
I will put it
as four
either
I can increase
the payment
of an employee
using the
employee one
instance
that we created
employee one
dot
increase pay
and then
how much percentage
you want to
increase
or else
I can call
the class itself
dot
you call the method
that we created
and then
we have to sell self
that self is basically
our employee one
and then
what is the percentage
percentage is four
and if I
execute this
again
print employee one dot
pay
I am going to get
all of these things
initially
8 lakhs
then 8 lakhs
is 32000
and then
8 lakhs
is 99000
so these are the
basics of the class
how to create
a class
inside the class
what is self?
how to declare variables
how you can
declare all of these things
and then
how you can create
the methods
so these are the basics
if you go back
to one of the code examples
maybe let's say
exceptions
and if you look at this one
here
what is the example
I created a class
which is basically
agent error
we will learn about
what is this
which is called as
inheritance
in the later video
so don't worry about that
inside this
we will learn
all of these things
what is super init?
we will learn
all of these things
in detail
so don't worry
after that
we have one more
function
and one more
method
and then
there is one more
class
and there is one more
and then
you can have
different different types of
classes for each use case
different methods
inside each of these classes
and in the next video
we are going to learn
which is called as
class variables
ENT
every single thing
we are going to learn
so don't worry
on that part
and stay tuned for the next one
and next one will be
on the Wednesday
blueprint. If you want to build a
house,
before you construct the house,
you will draw a blueprint,
right? So this house should be like
this,
and how to construct it.
Similarly, if you want to save